BETH: What are the main characteristics
found in individuals with Autism?
let’s have a look at these
in a little more detail.
JOE: ‘Communication’.
A child with autism may use different ways
to communicate, they may echo words and
phrases without context, take an adult to
something that they want, rather than ask
for it and take what is said literally.
Many individuals with autism have
good language skills, whilst others
will speak very little, or not at
all, though this does not mean they
cannot communicate in other ways.
Individuals with autism typically prefer
communication to be clear and simple.
BETH: ‘Social Interaction’.
Social situations are difficult
for individuals with Autism.
A child may prefer to play alone and
won’t respond to other adults or children.
Young people and adults typically struggle
with the ‘rules’ of social engagement,
such as when to speak, when to laugh and
when to empathise, and it can inhibit
their understanding of the ‘bigger
picture’ in relationships and contexts.
It may also cause problems in
education and the workplace.
JOE: ‘Repetitive and
Restrictive behaviour’
Children with autism can display
repetitive behaviour, including
hand flapping, toe walking,
spinning wheels, lining up toy cars.
Restrictive behaviour may mean a child
may only eat food of a certain colour,
have to walk the same route or only
watch one programme over and over.
As they get older individuals with
Autism may have a need for structure
and will impose their own routines in
order to help make sense of the world and
alleviate anxiety, and these can sometimes
become obsessive behaviours and rituals.
BETH: ‘Sensory sensitivity’
Sensory sensitivity is common
to the autism spectrum, this
may be ‘over sensitivity’ or
‘under-sensitivity’ to things such
as light, sound, touch and heat, or
certain tastes, textures or smells.
Sensory differences are most noticeable
when children are over-sensitive
to stimuli and may show distress
at loud noises or bright lights.
A young person or adult may also have
an exceptional attention to detail,
they may find working in a room
with certain sounds, raised voices,
flickering lights or cracks in the
wall will adversely affect them.
They may be affected by colours and
textures and the way things are laid
out, even changes in peoples appearance.
These sensitivities may lead to various
coping behaviours including avoidance of
certain places or people, rocking or even
using self-injury as a way of calming
the overload of sensations experienced.
JOE: ‘Fixation’.
Fixation is one of the characteristics
especially associated with high
functioning Autism spectrum disorder and
may involve subject or ideas fixation,
continually discussing the same topics
in conversation, obsessively playing the
same song repeatedly, or reading every
article written about a certain topic.
Many other high-functioning autistic
individuals have used their focus
on mathematics, biology, or writing
to inspire successful careers.
However, they may also experience
emotional sensitivity, social
difficulties, linguistic
oddities, devotion to routine
and dislike of change.
BETH: Fluctuation of Skills
Some autistic people have skills
and needs that ‘fluctuate’ from
day to day and moment to moment.
They may have over the years,
learned strategies which mask their
difficulties and characteristics.
The result is that the person with
autism can appear to be very distracted
and may seem to be day-dreaming, as
they are preoccupied with experiences
that others cannot appreciate.
Often autistic individuals are seen as
not having the ability to play or role
play, but that doesn’t mean that they
lack imagination and creative talent.
Some have narrow interests in a particular
topic or pastime and their obsessive
behaviour, means that they may focus
on that, often becoming extremely
knowledgeable or proficient in it.
This focus on detail can enable high
levels of achievement in certain fields.